<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-11-16T20:05:34-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Terra nullius</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Embodiment (II)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/16/embodiment-ii.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodiment (II)" /><published>2023-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/16/embodiment-ii</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/16/embodiment-ii.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Book</strong>: <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262720212/the-embodied-mind/">The Embodied Mind (Varela, Rosch, and Thompson, 1992)</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Book: The Embodied Mind (Varela, Rosch, and Thompson, 1992)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embodiment (I)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/embodiment-i.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embodiment (I)" /><published>2023-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-11-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/embodiment-i</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/11/01/embodiment-i.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Book</strong>: <a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262720212/the-embodied-mind/">The Embodied Mind (Varela, Rosch, and Thompson, 1992)</a></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/gray_arteries.jpg" alt="Arteries" /></p>
<figcaption>Detail from <i>Gray's Anatomy</i>, 1918. </figcaption>

<p>The mind is not an information processor. Chilean biologist Francisco Varela saw this clearly several decades ago. Reading <em>The Embodied Mind</em> was refreshing because I was able to share in Varela’s clarity at times, but it also left me with a lot of questions. What follows is a mix of reflection and context.</p>

<p>Varela, born and raised in Chile, finished his PhD in biology at Harvard in 1970, studying <em>information processing</em> in the insect visual system. Days after Varela returned from Harvard, Salvador Allende was elected president of Chile as the leader of a broad left-wing political coalition. Varela was a staunch supporter of Allende and a prominent member of a milieu where new ideas for democratic control of the economy along scientific principles were being proposed and tested. The national economy, conceptually freed a little from the anonymous demands of “the market”, was being re-understood and experimented with. While reckoning with this new world, Varela and mentor Humberto Maturana also went about the humble research program of defining life itself, a task that led them to the notion of <strong>autopoiesis</strong><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Even the most primitive living cell, at a high level of abstraction, is, you could say, analogous to a national economy: a set of processes (chemical in the one, social in the other) unified by (i) reproducing one another as a whole through time and (ii) maintaining the material conditions that allow for this reproduction. This was a promising line of thought.</p>

<p>In 1973, however, this period of intellectual and political optimism was ended by a violent US-backed military coup that led to Augusto Pinochet seizing power. Varela was deeply affected by the coup and lost friends and colleagues to the brutal machine of Pinochet’s police state, but managed to escape with his family to the US. Later in the 70s, probably not without reason, Varela delved into the practice of Buddhist meditation, finding teachers in the first wave of Tibetan monks to flee from the People’s Liberation Army in Tibet to practice in the West<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. This line of study made an impact on Varela: <em>The Embodied Mind</em> is in large part an effort to reconcile insights from Buddhist tradition and practice with open questions in Western cognitive science, and to sketch a new view of the mind that he calls <strong>enactivism</strong>.</p>

<p>To get to enactivism, we need to understand what it was a response to<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, i.e. what Varela calls <strong>cognitivism</strong>, and why <em>that</em> mode of thinking arose in the first place. Cognitivism, or, roughly, the idea of the information-processing mind, took hold in scientific circles over the 1950s and 60s (through figures like Noam Chomsky) for perfectly clear reasons. Preceding behavioral science (<strong>behaviorism</strong>) tended to see behavior as being determined fully by past conditioning (think Pavlov’s dogs), which had the shortcoming of leaving the present-tense mental process of the animal external to scientific understanding. However, developments in other fields provided a way to talk about this process: cryptographic advances necessitated by the Second World War had led to Claude Shannon’s mathematical theory of information, and in 1952 the first study of neural activity to model them as electrical circuits was published<sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. All the pieces were in place for the emergence of cognitivism as a <em>model</em> of mind, a way to specify its content: the cognitive process is a set of <em>computations performed by neural circuits on incoming sensory information</em>. Thought as the manipulation of symbols according to rules, the brain as a computer: slight caricatures of the cognitivist program, but not unfair ones.</p>

<p>This model was “wrong”, as they all are, but it was undoubtedly useful. Given the right experimental constraints, this actually is what some mental processes are like. However, through its utility the model became ingrained for some scientists as the automatic, unquestioned image of what the mind <em>is</em>. This line of thinking quickly ran into a wall: we may be able to fully understand the reaction a heavily anesthetized animal has to some simple stimulus (a green circle, a single musical note) in these terms, but even the decisionmaking of a fly evading a swatter (Varela’s example) is far too complex and multisensory to be tractable in this way. Instead of the two-way behaviorist split between behavior and an unknowable mind, the cognitivists ran into a three-way split between behavior, a model of cognition, and ineffable experience.</p>

<p>Varela’s “enactive” approach responds to this impasse by rethinking the problem using concepts from the Buddhist tradition. Varela understood systematic practice of meditation and associated textual &amp; pedagogic traditions to constitute a type of <strong>first-person science</strong>, with experience as its object. This was an insight that was new to me and felt like the central piece of the book. In the global history of intellectual exchange, this episode strikes me as particularly interesting: it brings together the threads of Tibetan Buddhist tradition, Marxist political action in Chile, European phenomenology<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>, and midcentury Harvard neuroscience in the figure of Francisco Varela. It’s fascinating to see that new formulations in abstract science are always already manifest in our practices, in the mundane repetitions of everyday life. Meditation is one such practice, one that has been extensively elaborated and written about across the 2,500 year Buddhist tradition (though I should say, I don’t think they have an exclusive claim on systematic introspection). Although I’m still groping toward a sense of Varela’s true relevance today, it’s clear he made an honest attempt at synthesizing these threads. I’ll leave it here for now but I intend to process the actual thought of the book a bit more in the next post. Thank you for reading or scrolling to the end of my first post.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Developed mainly in <em>Autopoiesis and Cognition</em> (1972), which I plan on reading at some point as well. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>He was even briefly taught by Chögyam Trungpa, who also taught the likes of David Bowie and Joni Mitchell. Varela also went on to found the <a href="https://www.mindandlife.org/about/#history">Mind and Life Institute</a> with the Dalai Lama, though what this collaboration really meant is still unclear to me. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>There is actually a middle term between cognitivism and enactivism (“emergence”) in the book, but I’ll save it for later. Too many -isms for one post. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><a href="doi:10.1113/jphysiol.1952.sp004764">Nobel prize-winning study in question</a> of the neuron that a squid uses to control its jet-propulsion predator escape mechanism: the largest neuron known and therefore the easiest to study using 1950s lab technology. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I’m less interested in this at the moment, and it’s not as central to the book, but it’s worth mentioning here that Varela also engages briefly with figures like Heidegger and Merleau-Ponty. Mostly they’re used to motivate the idea of systematically understanding experience, but the substance of the approach is distinctively Buddhist. <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Book: The Embodied Mind (Varela, Rosch, and Thompson, 1992)]]></summary></entry></feed>