<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-07-05T13:40:38-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">void fraction</title><subtitle>An analysis of the traversed, the not yet traversed, and the presently being traversed.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Cybernetic Middle Way</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/05/cybernagarjuna.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cybernetic Middle Way" /><published>2023-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/07/05/cybernagarjuna</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/07/05/cybernagarjuna.html"><![CDATA[<p>Cybernetic notions of life…</p>

<p>Nagarjuna claims objects have no svabhāva. That means organisms have no svabhāva.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Madhyamaka analysis of causation not a dyad, but a triad: cause, effect, and background of supporting conditions or <strong>causal field</strong>. Not every member of the causal field <strong>existentially</strong> depends on the effect they jointly bring about (if any of them are at all!) but the collection of these members as such exists <strong>only if there is some effect it causes</strong>. Assuming that for some objects to form a collection there must be something non-arbitrary that holds them together as one, cf. axiom of choice. Neither causal field, cause, nor effect exist independently of one another or of a cognizing subject (“partly habitual, partly deliberate process of cutting up the complex flow of phenomena into cognitively manageable bits”), <strong>they are empty of svabhāva</strong>. A causally produced object depends on its cause for existence and therefore doesn’t stand outside of dependence relations with other objects.</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Cybernetic notions of life…]]></summary></entry></feed>